# Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin

Zürich, Switzerland ibo.mohsin@gmail.com

Last Updated: August, 2022

https://ibomohsin.github.io/ linkedin.com/in/ibrahimalabdulmohsin/

I am a research scientist at Google Brain, developing tools for understanding deep learning and improving its societal impact, particularly relating to fairness. Previously, I founded and led the Advanced Analytics team at Saudi Aramco, managed the company's Enterprise Analytics program, and was a technical lead at its digital transformation program.

## **EDUCATION**

**Doctor of Philosophy - PhD, Computer Science**, *KAUST*, GPA: 4.0 / 4.0

Thesis title: "Learning via Query Synthesis." Committee: X. Zhang, X. Gao, D. Keyes (KAUST), and W. Wang (UCLA). 2012 — 2017

Master of Science, Electrical Engineering, Stanford University, GPA: 4.15 / 4.0

Emphasis on networked systems, artificial intelligence, and operations management. 2009-2011

Bachelor of Science, Computer Engineering, University of Nebraska, Lincoln, GPA: 3.98 / 4.0

Highest Distinction; Superior Scholarship Award; Minor in Economics. 2000 — 2005

## **SKILLS**

**Research & Development** Authored 1 book, +25 research papers, 1 granted patent and 3 pending patents.

**Communication** English (fluent), Arabic (native), German (elementary, A1).

**Technical** Data science, artificial intelligence, modeling & optimization, digital transformation, networked systems

(certified by Cisco, Juniper and Alcatel-Lucent).

Leadership +2 years managing corporate-wide enterprise analytics program, leading the data science team, and serv-

ing as a technical lead at the digital transformation program at Saudi Aramco.

## **SELECTED ACTIVITIES**

Program committee member at NeurIPS, ICML, ICLR, AAAI, and IJCAI.

Reviewer for TMLR, IEEE PAMI, IEEE TNNLS, and IEEE Communications Letters.

Member of the S20 Task Force (Digital Revolution).

Chair of AI track of the 2019 Arab-American Frontiers Symposium.

2017 — Present
2019 — Present
2020
2020

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## **RESEARCH & DEVELOPMENT SCIENTIST**

NOV 2019 — Present

Google, Brain Team

Zürich, Switzerland

- Led / co-led several projects to improve understanding of deep learning and improve ML fairness; e.g. pretraining with random labels, debiasing neural networks, debiasing multiclass datasets, data scaling laws, reinitialization and calibration.
- Key member of a moonshot team for machine learning fairness in healthcare.
- Member of the Google Scholarship Review Team and mentor of AI residents.

## LEAD, ADVANCED ANALYTICS

 $\mathsf{NOV}\,2017-\mathsf{OCT}\,2019$ 

Saudi Aramco, Corporate Applications Dept

Dhahran, Saudi Arabia

- Founded and led the Advanced Analytics team that was responsible for developing AI solutions, managing analytics infrastructures, conducting research collaboration with academia, evaluating technologies, and developing roadmaps.
- Technical lead at the Digital Transformation Program, with a mission to accelerate the adoption of artificial intelligence at the company.
- Led the design & implementation of several ML applications in sectors such as downstream, supply chain, sales & marketing, IT,
   cybersecurity and HR.

#### **NETWORK PERFORMANCE ENGINEER**

JUN 2011 — AUG 2012

Dhahran, Saudi Arabia

Saudi Aramco, Comm. Eng. Department

Saudi Aramco, Comm. Eng. Department

- Won the Operation Services Business Line recognition award (2012) for "distinguished achievements."
- Performance management and capacity planning for enterprise communications services such as the Data Center, the Internet,
   Extranet, and Wireless LAN infrastructures.
- Developed an analytics tool for automated performance analysis and SLA compliance assessment.

# **DATA NETWORK ENGINEER**

JUL 2005 — AUG 2009

Dhahran, Saudi Arabia

- Won the Information Technology Admin Area recognition award (2007) for "developing innovative solutions" and the Communications Eng Dept recognition award (2009) for "significant contributions to department's success."
- Key member of an 18-month IT network security project for securing critical facilities.
- Project manager for a 1-year CCTV surveillance camera systems project (involving civil and communications work).
- Design, installation, configuration, reviews, upgrades, and troubleshooting of data networks.

# Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin

Zürich, Switzerland ibo.mohsin@gmail.com

Last Updated: August, 2022 linkedin.com/in/ibrahimalabdulmohsin/

https://ibomohsin.github.io/

# Воокѕ

Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin, Summability Calculus: A Comprehensive Theory of Fractional Finite Sums, Springer, 2018.

## RECENT PREPRINTS

- <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>, Nicole Chiou, Alexander D'Amour, Arthur Gretton, Sanmi Koyejo, Matt J. Kusner, Stephen R. Pfohl, Olawale Salaudeen, Jessica Schrouff, Katherine Tsai: "*Adapting to Latent Subgroup Shifts via Concepts and Proxies.*", arXiv:2212.11254, 2022.
- Lucas Beyer, Pavel Izmailov, Alexander Kolesnikov, Mathilde Caron, Simon Kornblith, Xiaohua Zhai, Matthias Minderer, Michael Tschannen, Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin, Filip Pavetic: "FlexiViT: One Model for All Patch Sizes.", arXiv:2212.08013, 2022.
- Amr Khalifa\*, Michael C. Mozer, Hanie Sedghi, Behnam Neyshabur, <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>\*: "Layer-Stack Temperature Scaling." arXiv:2211.10193, 2022.

## **PUBLICATIONS**

- <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>, Behnam Neyshabur, Xiaohua Zhai: "Revisiting Neural Scaling Laws in Language and Vision.", NeurIPS, 2022.
- <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>, Jessica Schrouff, Oluwasanmi Koyejo: "A Reduction to Binary Approach for Debiasing Multiclass Datasets.", **NeurIPS**, 2022.
- Jessica Schrouff, Natalie Harris, Oluwasanmi Koyejo, <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>, Eva Schnider, Krista Opsahl-Ong, Alexander Brown, Subhrajit Roy, Diana Mincu, Christina Chen, Awa Dieng, Yuan Liu, Vivek Natarajan, Alan Karthikesalingam, Katherine A. Heller, Silvia Chiappa, Alexander D'Amour: "Maintaining fairness across distribution shift: do we have viable solutions for real-world applications?", NeurIPS, 2022.
- Alexander Soen, <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>, Sanmi Koyejo, Yishay Mansour, Nyalleng Moorosi, Richard Nock, Ke Sun, Lexing Xie: "Fair Wrapping for Black-box Predictions.", **NeurIPS**, 2022.
- Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin, Mario Lucic: "A Near-Optimal Algorithm for Debiasing Trained Machine Learning Models.", NeurIPS, 2021.
- Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin, Larisa Markeeva, Daniel Keysers, Ilya O. Tolstikhin: "A Generalized Lottery Ticket Hypothesis.", SNN, 2021.
- <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>, Hartmut Maennel, Daniel Keysers: "The Impact of Reinitialization on Generalization in Convolutional Neural Networks.", CoRR abs/2109.00267, 2021.
- <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>: "A Generalization of Classical Formulas in Numerical Integration and Series Convergence Acceleration.", CoRR abs/2106.07621, 2021.
- Hartmut Maennel\*, <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>\*, Ilya O. Tolstikhin, Robert J. N. Baldock, Olivier Bousquet, Sylvain Gelly, Daniel Keysers: "What Do Neural Networks Learn When Trained With Random Labels?", **NeurIPS**, 2020.
- <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>: "Towards a Unified Theory of Learning and Information.", **Entropy** 22(4), 2020.
- <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>: "Information Theoretic Guarantees for Empirical Risk Minimization with Applications to Model Selection and Large-Scale Optimization.", **ICML**, 2018.
- <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>: "Axiomatic Characterization of AdaBoost and the Multiplicative Weight Update Procedure.", **ECML/PKDD**, 2018.
- <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>: "An Information-Theoretic Route from Generalization in Expectation to Generalization in Probability., **AISTATS**, 2017.
- <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>, Moustapha Cisse, Xin Gao, Xiangliang Zhang: "*Large margin classification with indefinite similarities*", **Machine Learning Journal** 103(2), 2016.
- <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>, Yufei Han, Yun Shen, Xiangliang Zhang: "Content-Agnostic Malware Detection in Heterogeneous Malicious Distribution Graph", CIKM, 2016.
- <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>, Moustapha Cissé, Xiangliang Zhang: "Is Attribute-Based Zero-Shot Learning an Ill-Posed Strategy?", **ECML/PKDD**, 2016.
- Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin, Xin Gao, Xiangliang Zhang: "Efficient Active Learning of Halfspaces via Query Synthesis", AAAI, 2015.
- Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin: "Algorithmic Stability and Uniform Generalization.", NeurIPS, 2015.
- Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin, Xin Gao, Xiangliang Zhang: "Support vector machines with indefinite kernels.", ACML, 2014.
- <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>, Xin Gao, Xiangliang Zhang: "Adding Robustness to Support Vector Machines Against Adversarial Reverse Engineering.", CIKM, 2014.
- <u>Ibrahim Alabdulmohsin</u>, Amal Hyadi, Laila H. Afify, Basem Shihada: "*End-to-end delay analysis in wireless sensor networks with service vacation.*", **WCNC**, 2014.